The Life Of Muhammad ﷺ Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Dear brothers and sisters,
السلام وعليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
After, a life of hypocrisy of plotting and planning against Rasool Allah ﷺ
Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) was laying down on his deathbed, Rasool Allah ﷺ visited him.
And this is according to Muhammad Bin Is'haq(محمد بن اسحاق).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ when he saw in his face, the signs of death.
He told him;
اَمَا وَللهِ اِنْ كُنْتُ لَأَنْهَاكَ عَنْ حُبِّ يَهُوْدَ
In the name of Allah, I used to warn you from loving the Jews.
So, Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) said;
قَدْ أَبْغَضَهُمْ أَسْعَدْ بِنْ زُرَارَةْ فَمَهَ
As'ad Bin Zurarah(أَسْعَدْ بِنْ زُرَارَةْ), he despised them, and what did that do for him.?
So, until his last moment Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) was still having split loyalties.
And this shows us an important sign of the hypocrites
and that is that they have loyalty to the Kuffar(كُفَّار)
and they have loyalty to the Christians and the Jews.
And this is a sign that has repeated itself in Qur'an, more than once.
فَتَرَى الَّذِينَ فِي قُلُوبِهِمْ مَرَضٌ يُسَارِعُونَ فِيهِمْ
You see that the ones, who have a disease in their heart, these are the Munafiqeen(منافقين)
they are hasting towards them, towards the disbelievers.
So, the Munafiqeen(منافقين) cannot get this love of the Kuffar(كفار) out of their hearts.
In Sahih Al-Bukhari(صحيح ألبخاري), when Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبدالله بن ابي) passed away,
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to pray on his Janazah(جنازة).
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) came and stood in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him;
يا رسول الله: تُصَلِّيْ عَلَيْهِ وَقَدْ قَالَ فِيْ يَوْمِ كَذَا وَكَذَا، وَقَالَ فِيْ يَوْمِ كَذَا كَذَا وَكَذَا
Are you gonna pray on him when he said;
On such and such day this and that, and he said on this day this and that.?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is going through the past of Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبدالله بن ابي)
he's reminding Rasool Allah ﷺ with the positions that Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) was taking.
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded back and said;
دَعْنِيْ يَا عُمَرْ فَإِنِّيْ بَيْنَ خَيْرَتَيْنِ
وَلَوْ أَعْلَمْ أَنِّيْ إِنْ زِدْتُّ عَلَى السَبْعِيْنَ غُفِرَ لَه’ لَزِدْتُ
O Umar(عمر) leave me alone.
If I know that if I ask Allah to forgive him more than seventy times, it would be accepted, I would do that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is referring to the Ayah(آية) verse eighty, Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة),
اِسْتَغْفِرْ لَهُمْ أَوْ لَا تَسْتَغْفِرْ لَهُمْ
إِنْ تَسْتَغْفِرْ لَهُمْ سَبْعِينَ مَرَّةً فَلَنْ يَغْفِرَ اللَّهُ لَهُمْ
ذَٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُمْ كَفَرُوا بِاللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ ۗ وَاللَّهُ لَا يَهْدِي الْقَوْمَ الْفَاسِقِينَ۝
Ask forgiveness for them, O Muhammad(محمد) or do not ask forgiveness for them.
If you should ask forgiveness for them 70 times never will Allah forgive them.
That is because they disbelieved in Allah and His Messenger
and Allah does not guide the defiantly disobedient people.
So, here you see in the Ayah(آية), Allah saying 70 times.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
If I know that if I do more than 70, Allah will forgive him, I would do so.
Dear Brothers and Sisters, this shows us a quality in Rasool Allah ﷺ that is striking.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has suffered personally, again and again from Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي)
directly and indirectly the plots and the plans and the deception and the lies of Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) are countless.
Nevertheless, Rasool Allah ﷺ is still willing to give him a last chance to pray on his Janazah(جنازة) and to ask Allah, to forgive him.
It shows you, how Rasool Allah ﷺ was willing to go out of his way to give his followers another opportunity.
But then Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية) verse 84, in Surah Taubah(سورة التوبة);
وَلَا تُصَلِّ عَلَىٰ أَحَدٍ مِنْهُمْ مَاتَ أَبَدًا وَلَا تَقُمْ عَلَىٰ قَبْرِهِ
إِنَّهُمْ كَفَرُوا بِاللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ وَمَاتُوا وَهُمْ فَاسِقُونَ۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
And do not pray over any of them who has died ever, or stand at his grave.
Indeed, they disbelieved in Allah and His Messenger and died,
while they were defiantly disobedient.
So, now the issue is clarified
that no Salah(صلاة) should be on offered on the Munafiqeen(منافقين) and this is the final Hukum(حكم),
this is the final judgment on the issue.
And this is one of the incidents in which the Qur'an supported the opinion of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
It is Hikmah(حكمة) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ that Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) would not survive Muhammadﷺ
and he would actually die before him.
Because Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) was living with hope, with aspirations
that by being patient, and by not facing the Muslims directly, like the Kuffar(كفار) are doing
but by choosing the path of Nifaaq(نفاق)
he would be able to go through what he perceives as a temporary phase.
And that in the end, he and his people and his ideas would survive.
That's the thinking that they used to have.
That by sitting tight and waiting, they have a chance and that this Islam thing is a temporary thing.
It's a phase that's going to come and go and people are going to get back to normal.
And he was living with these hopes
especially that he felt that it was Muhammadﷺ, who stripped him, of his power and authority.
Because as it says in the books of Seerah(سيرة),
his people were planning to appoint him as king over them.
And that is when Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة) and his plans were shattered.
So, Abdullah Bin Obbaye(عبد الله بن أبي) ended up dying before Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And the religion of Islam survived.
And the way of the Munafiqeen(منافقين) is a way that dies
and they face Allahعَزّوجَلّ on the day of judgment, and have to face His wrath.
Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرى) to make Hajj(حج).
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was to lead the delegation of Hajj(حج) not Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to make Hajj(حج),
while the false gods are lining up around the Al-Ka'aba(ألكعبه).
Ya'ani(يعنى) obviously the idols themselves were already destroyed, but the followers are still coming,
because Shirk(شرك) was still surviving in some parts of Arabia.
Plus, they also had the tradition of doing Tawaf(طواف) naked
they used to believe that, because of their sins, because of their impurity they cannot come with these clothes on.
So, they would take off their clothes
and then borrow some clothes from the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
they used to view them as being special, Al-Humus(ألحمص).
So they will borrow clothes from them.
But some people were not in the position of borrowing, they don't have any money, they don't have any status to borrow
so they would end up making Tawaf(طواف) naked.
So, you had the dual problem of having Mushrikeen(مشركين) and having naked people go around Al-Ka'aba(ألكعبه).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to attend Al-Hajj(ألحج) while this Munkar(منكر), this evil was going on.
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه led the Muslims in Al-Hajj(ألحج),
it says that they were a few hundred Sahabah(صحابه), who went with him to make Hajj(حج).
And after he left, Rasool Allah ﷺ, received the first part of Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to send these Ayaat(آيات) to Makkah, so that the people would hear them.
So, they said: Shall we send them to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبو بكر ألصديق)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No.
only a man from my household should convey these announcements from me.
And he called Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and he told him to go to Makkah, and to announce the following;
لَا يُؤَدِّيْ عَنِّي إِلَّا رَجُلٌ مِنْ أَهْلِ بَيْتِيْ ثُمَّ دَعَا عَليَّ بِنَ أَبِيْ طَالِبٍ فَقَالْ اُخْرِجْ بِهَذِه الْقِصَّةِ مِنْ صَدْرِ بَرَاءَةَ
وَأَذِّنْ فِي النَّاسِ يَوْمِ النَّحَرِ إِذَا اجْتَمَعُوْا بِمِنَى أَلَا إِنَّهُ لَا يَدْخُلُ الْجنَّةَ كَافرٌ
وَلَا يَحُجُّ بَعْدَ الْعَامِ مُشْرِكٌ
وَلَا يَطُوْفُ بِاْلَبَيْتِ عُرْيَانٌ
وَمَنْ كَانَ لَهُ عِنْدَ رَسُوْلِ اللَّهِ صلى الله عليه وسلم عَهْدٌ فَهُوَ لَهُ إِلَى مُدَّتِهِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب): Go with these verses from Surah Al-Bara'aa(سورة ألبرآءة)
and announce them, to the people, declare them to the people, when they are gathering in Minaa(منى)
and tell them that no, disbeliever shall enter into paradise.
And no polytheist shall make Hajj(حج) after this year.
And no, naked person shall do Tawaf(طواف) around the house of Allah.
And whoever has a contract of security from Rasool Allah ﷺ
then his contract will be fulfilled until the end of its duration.
And then he had to read the Ayaat(آيات) of Surah At-Taubah(سورة التوبة).
We'll just read the first five Ayaat(آيات).
بَرَاءَةٌ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ إِلَى الَّذِينَ عَاهَدْتُمْ مِنَ الْمُشْرِكِينَ۝
This is a declaration of disassociation from Allah and His Messenger
to those with whom you had made a treaty among the polytheists.
Notice that the Surah(سورة) of Bara'aa(برآءة) which is Taubah(ألتوبة) is the only Surah(سورة) in Qur'an that does not start with
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَٰنِ الرَّحِيمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَٰنِ الرَّحِيمِ ۝
Includes the name of Allah, the Merciful.
And this is a straightforward declaration of disassociation from the Kuffar(كفار)
and therefore it does not start with
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَٰنِ الرَّحِيمِ۝
It starts with Bara'aa(برآءة), disassociation.
That's the first word in this Surah(سورة) disavowal, disassociation, being free from them.
This is a declaration of disassociation from Allah and His Messenger
to those with whom you had made the treaty among the polytheists.
فَسِيحُوا فِي الْأَرْضِ أَرْبَعَةَ أَشْهُرٍ
وَاعْلَمُوا أَنَّكُمْ غَيْرُ مُعْجِزِي اللَّهِ ۙ وَأَنَّ اللَّهَ مُخْزِي الْكَافِرِينَ۝
So, travel freely, O disbelievers throughout the land, during four months
but know that you cannot cause failure to Allah and that Allah will disgrace the disbelievers.
So, they were given four months.
وَأَذَانٌ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ إِلَى النَّاسِ يَوْمَ الْحَجِّ الْأَكْبَرِ أَنَّ اللَّهَ
أَنَّ اللَّهَ بَرِيءٌ مِنَ الْمُشْرِكِينَ ۙ وَرَسُولُهُ ۚ
فَإِنْ تُبْتُمْ فَهُوَ خَيْرٌ لَكُمْ ۖ وَإِنْ تَوَلَّيْتُمْ فَاعْلَمُوا أَنَّكُمْ غَيْرُ مُعْجِزِي اللَّهِ
وَبَشِّرِ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا بِعَذَابٍ أَلِيمٍ۝
And it is an announcement from Allah and His messenger to the people on the day of the greater pilgrimage
that Allah is disassociated from the disbelievers and so is, His Messenger.
So, if you repent, that is best for you.
But if you turn away then know that you will not cause failure to Allah
and give glad tidings to those, who disbelieve, of a painful punishment.
إِلَّا الَّذِينَ عَاهَدْتُمْ مِنَ الْمُشْرِكِينَ ثُمَّ لَمْ يَنْقُصُوكُمْ شَيْئًا
ثُمَّ لَمْ يَنْقُصُوكُمْ شَيْئًا وَلَمْ يُظَاهِرُوا عَلَيْكُمْ أَحَدًا
فَأَتِمُّوا إِلَيْهِمْ عَهْدَهُمْ إِلَىٰ مُدَّتِهِمْ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ يُحِبُّ الْمُتَّقِينَ۝
فَإِذَا انْسَلَخَ الْأَشْهُرُ الْحُرُمُ فَاقْتُلُوا الْمُشْرِكِينَ حَيْثُ وَجَدْتُمُوهُمْ
وَخُذُوهُمْ وَاحْصُرُوهُمْ وَاقْعُدُوا لَهُمْ كُلَّ مَرْصَدٍ ۚ
فَإِنْ تَابُوا وَأَقَامُوا الصَّلَاةَ وَآتَوُا الزَّكَاةَ فَخَلُّوا سَبِيلَهُمْ ۚ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ غَفُورٌ رَحِيمٌ۝
Accepted are those, with whom you made a treaty among the polytheists
and then they have not been deficient towards you in anything, or supported anyone against you,
so complete for them their treaty until, their term has ended.
Indeed, Allah loves the righteous who fear Him.
And when the sacred months have passed, then kill the polytheists wherever you find them
and capture them and besiege them, and sit in, and wait for them at every place of ambush.
But if they should repent, establish prayer and give Zaka'at(زكواة), let them go on their way.
Indeed, Allah is Forgiving and Merciful.
These are the Ayaat(آيات) and more, that Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) announced to the disbelievers
in the Hajj(حج) of the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرة).
And it was the last year in which the Mushrikeen(مشركين) are going to make Hajj(حج)
and it was the last year, when the traditions and rituals of disbelief are going to be shown in Makkah.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِذَا جَاءَ نَصْرُ اللَّهِ وَالْفَتْحُ۝
وَرَأَيْتَ النَّاسَ يَدْخُلُونَ فِي دِينِ اللَّهِ أَفْوَاجًا۝
فَسَبِّحْ بِحَمْدِ رَبِّكَ وَاسْتَغْفِرْهُ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ تَوَّابًا۝
When the victory of Allah has come and the conquest and you see
the people entering into the religion of Allah in multitudes
then exalt Him with praise of your Lord and ask forgiveness of Him.
Indeed, He is ever Accepting of repentance.
When the victory of Allah has come and the conquest
the result of that would be that people will enter into Islam
as it's mentioned in the books of Seerah(سيرة),
that the tribes of Arabia, were watching the conflict between Rasool Allah ﷺ and Quraish(قريش),
and they were waiting to see who will win.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ defeated Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), the Arabs then came in multitudes accepting Islam.
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) was seen as the religious authority,
they are the keepers of the house of Allah,
they are the ones, who manage the affairs of the people in Hajj(حج) and Umrah(عمره),
they are the ones, who live in Makkah,
and Makkah was the religious center of the Arabs.
So, people used to look up to them.
And when Muhammadﷺ announced the Prophet hood
and the war between him and Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) started,
many of them wanted to sit on the sidelines and not take a position
until, they see where this conflict is heading.
After Makkah was opened.
And then pretty soon after that
the tribes around Makkah started accepting Islam such as Hawazin(هوازن) and many of them became Muslim.
And then after that Thaqeef(ثقيف) they also came and accepted Islam
and we talked about how they were besieged in At-Taef(الطائف) and Rasool Allah ﷺ left them.
Eventually they came with their own choice and accepted Islam.
So, you have Quraish(قريش), and Thaqeef(ثقيف), the largest and most important two tribes in the area accepting Islam.
After that, people were just flooding into Madina accepting Islam.
So, the ninth year of Hijrah(هجرى) was called Aam-El-Wafood(عام الوفود), the year of delegations.
These tribes would send their representatives to Madina
and they would pledge allegiance to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And this pledge of allegiance, was also a pledge of allegiance to the Islamic State.
And it's not like they're only accepting Islam and then leaving.
No, they are becoming part of the political entity of Madina
because the Bay'ah(بيعة) that they are giving is the Bay'ah(بيعة) to the head of state, Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, they are accepting his Hukum(حكم), they're accepting his rule.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) and Ibn Ishaaq(ابن اسحاق) and Al-Waqadi(الواقعدي), they mentioned many delegations.
I will go through some of them.
And we need to keep in mind here that
even though these all became Muslim, and they are counted as Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
but it is considered that whoever became Muslim before the conquest of Makkah
has a higher status than those who became Muslim after the conquest of Makkah.
Why? Because after the conquest of Makkah, it was becoming very clear
that victory in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is for the Muslims,
but the ones, who accepted Islam before that
for them, becoming Muslim was a choice that they would make, and they would know,
that would they would face hardship and would have to make sacrifice.
So the earlier you became Muslim, the more difficult it was.
And that's why Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
لَا يَسْتَوِي مِنْكُمْ مَنْ أَنْفَقَ مِنْ قَبْلِ الْفَتْحِ وَقَاتَلَ ۚ
أُولَٰئِكَ أَعْظَمُ دَرَجَةً مِنَ الَّذِينَ أَنْفَقُوا مِنْ بَعْدُ وَقَاتَلُوا ۚ
وَكُلًّا وَعَدَ اللَّهُ الْحُسْنَىٰ ۚ
Allah says in Surah Al-Hadeed(سورة الحديد)
not equal among you are those who spent before the conquest
and this is referring to the conquest of Makkah
and fought and those who did so after it,
those are greater in degree then they who spent afterwards and fought.
The people of Thaqeef(ثقيف), they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they accepted Islam.
And it says in the narration that they tried to negotiate with Rasool Allah ﷺ to leave their major idol for a year.
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused, they said: Then leave it for a month,
because they were worried that the commoners among the people will be shocked
and wouldn't be able to handle seeing their so called God fall down into rubble, fall down into pieces.
So, they wanted to take it slowly with the people, so they said;
We will accept Islam but we don't want our idol to be destroyed except after a year from now
so that we could take it step by step with the people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused.
They said: A month! He refused.
A week! He refused.
A day! He refused.
And they tried their best to negotiate with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Ullah made it clear that he's not going to approve such a thing
false god to stay for an additional moment was unacceptable.
So, then they said: If that's the case, then we are not going to bring it down,
send somebody from your end to do it.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) and Al-Mugheera Bin Sho'ba(مغيرة بن شعبة), who is from Thaqeef(ثقيف).
They both went and people started saying wait for diseases
wait for leprosy, wait for…. they are threatening.
They're threatening and they were serious.
They were threatening Al-Mugheerah Bin Sho'ba(المغيرة بن شعبة) that the gods will destroy you.
So, it says that he wanted to make fun of this thought of theirs.
So, he struck the idol with his axe and then he pretended that he fell down.
So, they all started screaming and shouting, happy that the gods have struck back against Al-Mugheerah Bin Sho'ba(المغيرة بن شعبة).
And then he stood up and said: You are fools, this is nothing but a piece of stone.
And he started breaking it into pieces.
And then we have the delegation that came from Bannu Tamim(بنوتميم)
They came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he gave them the glad tidings.
This is in Bukhari(بخاريْ)
اِقْبَلُوا الْبُشْرَى يَا بَنِى تَمِيمٍ
Accept the glad tidings O, Bani Tamim(بني تميم).
قَالُوا يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ قَدْ بَشَّرْتَنَا فَأَعْطِنَا
O Rasool Ullah: We have heard that now give us,
we don't want good news, we don't want glad tidings, we want you to give us something.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ did not like that
and then there were people, who came from Yemen.
So, he told them;
اِقْبَلُوا الْبُشْرَى إِذْ لَمْ يَقْبَلْهَا بَنُو تَمِيمٍ
Accept the glad tidings since Bannu Tamim(بنوتميم) did not accept them.
فَقَالُوا قَدْ قَبِلْنَا يَا رَسُولَ اللَّهِ
We accepted O Rasool Ullah.
Anyway, when a delegation come it is Rasool Allah ﷺ, who would then appoint among them, a leader.
So, when Bannu Tamim(بنوتميم) came, there were two major leaders among them,
one is Al-Akrah Bin Habis(الأَقْرَعَ بْنَ حَابِسٍ) and the other one is Al-QahQah Bin Ma'bad Bin Zararah(الْقَعْقَاعَ بْنَ مَعْبَدِ بْنِ زُرَارَةَ).
So, it says in Bukhari(بخاريْ) that
Abu Bakr رضي الله عنه suggested to Rasool Allah ﷺ to appoint Al-QahQah Bin Ma'bad(الْقَعْقَاعَ بْنَ مَعْبَدِ) to be their leader.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: No! Appoint Al-Akrah Bin Habis(الأَقْرَعَ بْنَ حَابِسٍ).
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) became angry and said: You said that only to go against my opinion.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
مَا أَرَدْتُ خِلاَفَكَ
I did not do that to go against your opinion.
And then, they started arguing with each other and their voices became loud.
And that is when Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية):
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا لَا تُقَدِّمُوا بَيْنَ يَدَيِ اللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ
O, you who have believed! Do not put yourselves before Allah and His Messenger but fear Allah,
indeed Allah is Hearing and Knowing.
This is the first Ayah(آية) in Surah Al-Hujraat(سورة ألحجرات).
And then there's the delegation from Bannu Abd Al-Qais(بنوعبدالقيس),
these are from the extreme eastern part of the Arabian Peninsula.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
آمُرُكُمْ بِأَرْبَعٍ ، وَأَنْهَاكُمْ عَنْ أَرْبَعٍ الإِيمَانِ بِاللَّهِ ، هَلْ تَدْرُونَ مَا الإِيمَانُ بِاللَّهِ ؟
شَهَادَةُ أَنْ لاَ إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ ، وَإِقَامُ الصَّلاَةِ ، وَإِيتَاءُ الزَّكَاةِ ، وَصَوْمُ رَمَضَانَ ، وَأَنْ تُعْطُوا مِنَ المَغَانِمِ الخُمُسَ
وَأَنْهَاكُمْ عَنْ أَرْبَعٍ ، مَا انْتُبِذَ فِي الدُّبَّاءِ ، وَالنَّقِيرِ ، وَالحَنْتَمِ ، وَالمُزَفَّتِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I command you with four, and I warn you from four.
I command you to believe in Allah and do you know what believe in Allah means.?
To testify that there's no one worthy of worship but Allah
to establish Salah(صلاة), to pay Zakat(زكواة), to fast Ramadhan(رمضان), and to give the one fifth of the booty.
Because they are going to fight Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
and the rule is that when you gain any spoils of war,
you have to give one fifth of them to the leader.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them: And I warn you from four things.
And these are four different types of containers that they used to use, for drinking their alcohol.
So, they were told not to drink alcohol and also not to use those containers
to get them out of the habit of drinking.
And then there's the incident of Thumamah رضي الله عنه.
Now, this is mentioned among the delegations even though it doesn't belong here.
Because Thumamah(ثمامة), first of all, did not come to Madina by will, but he was arrested and captured.
And second of all, this incident happened before
because Thumamah(ثمامة) is talking about Makkah being Kuffar(كفار) at the time
and now we're talking about a time when Makkah was already Muslim.
But this is where Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر), puts it in the sequence
and you would find it in the books of Seerah(سيرة) also within the Aam-El-Wafood(عام الوفود).
Apparently they gathered all of the delegations that would come in one section
even though the timing might not have been the same.
For example, they talk about to Tufail Bin Amr Ad-Doasi(طفيل بن عمرو ألدوسي),
even though he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ in Makkah not in Madina.
Anyway, Rasool Allah ﷺ sent an army to Najd(نجد)
and they arrested the man from Banni Haneefah(بني حنيفه).
They captured the man from Banni Haneefah(بني حنيفه), his name is to Thumamah Bin Athaal(ثمامة بن أثال).
They bound him to a pillar in the Masjid(مسجد).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ went to him and said;
مَا عِنْدَكَ يَا ثُمَامَةْ؟
What do you have to say;
فَقَالَ: عِنْدِيْ خَيْرِ يَا مُحَمَّدْ
I have good to say,
إِنْ تَقْتُلْنِيْ تَقْتُلْ ذَا دَمْ
If you kill me, then you would kill a man, who is very worthy among his people.
I mean, if you do kill me, you would have killed somebody who's important.
That's one interpretation.
The other interpretation it means that you have killed someone who has blood on his hands,
and therefore there's no blame on you, if you do so.
وَإِنْ تُنْعِمْ تُنْعِمْ عَلَى شَاكِرْ،
But if you release me, you would release a person, who's grateful.
وَإِنْ كُنْتَ تُرِيْدَ الْمَالْ، فَسَلْ مِنْه مَا شِئْتَ،
And if you want money, ask me what you want.
Rasool Ullah left him.
Then he came to him the next day and said; What do you have to say?
He said the same thing?
عِنْدِيْ مَا قُلْتُ لَكْ
I have, what I already told you.
If you release me, You are releasing a man, who is grateful.
And then he came to him the next day and told him, what do you have to say Thumamah(ثمامة)?
He said: I have to say what you already heard.
فقال : أَطْلِقُوْا ثُمَامَة
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Release him.
He left and as soon as he got out of the Masjid(مسجد), he took a Ghusal(غسل), he bathed.
And then he entered in the Masjid(مسجد) and said;
أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله، وأشهد أن محمد رسول الله،
He didn't want to do it when he was tied, but now he's grateful.
And he's free, he could leave if he wants.
But he became Muslim and he said;
يَا محمد، وَالله مَا كَانَ عَلَى وَجْهِ الْأرْضَ وَجْه أَبْغَضَ إِلَيَّ مِنْ وَجْهِكَ
There was no face on the face of the earth, that was more despised to me than your face.
فَقَدْ أَصْبَحَ وَجْهُكَ أَحَبُّ الْوُجُوْهُ اِلَيْ
Now, your face is the most beloved to me.
وَالله مَا كَانَ مِنْ دِيْنٌ أَبْغَضَ إِلَىَّ مِنْ دِيْنَكْ، فَأَصْبَحَ دِيْنَكْ أَحَبْ الدِّيْنَ إِلَيَّ،
There was no religion that was more despised to me than your religion.
And now your religion has become the most beloved to me.
وَاللهِ مَا كَانَ مِنْ بَلَدِ أَبْغَضَ إِلَيَّ مِنْ بَلَدِكَ، فَأَصْبَحَ بَلَدِكَ أَحَبَّ الْبِلَادِ إِلَيْ،
And there was no land that was more despised to me than your land.
And now your land is the most beloved to me.
وَإنَّ خَيْلَكَ أخَذَتْنِي وأَنَا أُرِيدُ العُمْرَةَ، فَمَاذَا تَرَى؟
And your horsemen have captured me and I wanted to go to Umrah(عمرة),
what do you think, I should do?
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him to go and make Umrah(عمرة).
So, when he arrived to Makkah, they told him.
اصَبَوْتَ
Did you become an apostate?
That's what they would tell people, who become Muslim.
قَالَ: لَا،
No, but I am become Muslim with Muhammadﷺ and then he said;
لَا واللَّهِ، لا تَأْتِيكُمْ مِنَ اليَمَامَةِ حَبَّةُ حِنْطَةٍ، حتَّى يَأْذَنَ فِيهَا النبيُّ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ
And In the name of Allah, not one single grain of wheat would reach you from Yamamah(يمامه)
until, Rasool Allah ﷺ allows it to you.
And this is an evidence used by those, who accept the procedure of boycotting as a valid weapon of war.
Because Thumamah(ثمامه) what he did.?
Was actually an economical boycott on Makkah
he prevented the caravans from carrying wheat to Makkah.
So, they say that this is evidence boycotting the enemy is a valid way of fighting them.
And then there's a delegation of Bannu Haneefah(بنوحنيفه) which included a man called Musailimah(مسيلمه).
عَنِ ابْنِ عَبَّاسٍ قَالَ: قَدِمَ مُسَيْلِمَةُ الْكَذَّابُ عَلَى عَهْدِ رَسُولِ اللَّهِ  صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ ، فَجَعَلَ يَقُولُ
إِنْ جَعَلَ لِي مُحَمَّدٌ الْأَمْرَ مِنْ بَعْدِهِ اتَّبَعْتُهُ،
Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) says, that Musaylima(مسيلمه), the liar, came to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he was saying if Muhammad(محمد) is going to appoint me to lead after him, I would follow him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ came to him along with Thabit Bin Qais Bin Shammas(ثابت بن قيس بن شماس)
and Rasool Ullah had in his hand a piece of wood from a palm tree, from the leaves of a palm tree.
And then he told Musaylima(مسيلمه) and he's among his people.
لَوْ سَأَلتَنِي هَذِهِ الْقِطْعَةَ مَا أَعْطَيْتُكَهَا
If you ask me to give you this, I wouldn't give it to you.
Let alone giving you the leadership of the Ummah(امة), after me.
I wouldn't even give you this piece of Palm Leave and then Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
وَلَنْ تَعْدُوَ أَمْرَ اللَّهِ فِيكَ
And you're not gonna surpass, what Allah has destined for you.
وَلَئِنْ أَدْبَرْتَ لَيَعْقِرَنَّكَ اللَّهُ،
And if you leave, Allah will destroy you.
وَإِنِّي لَأَرَاكَ الَّذِي أُرِيتُ فِيكَ مَا رَأَيْتُ،
And I think that you are the one, whom I have seen what I saw,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ is referring to a dream that he has seen.
وَهَذَا ثَابِتٌ يُجِيبُكَ عَنِّي
And here is Thabit(ثابت), he will speak to you on my behalf and then Rasool Ullah left.
The dream that Rasool Allah ﷺ is referring to,
بَيْن أنا نائِمٌ رَأَيْتُ في يَدَيَّ سِوارَيْنِ مِن ذَهَبٍ،
فأهَمَّنِي شَأْنُهُما، فَأُوحِيَ إلَيَّ في المَنامِ أنِ انْفُخْهُما، فَنَفَخْتُهُما فَطارا
فأوَّلْتُهُما كَذّابَيْنِ يَخْرُجانِ مِن بَعْدِيْ، أحَدُهُما اَسْوَد اَلْعَنْسِيَّ ، والآخَرُ مُسَيْلِمَةَ
Rasool Allah said صلاوة الله وسلام عليه,
While I was asleep I saw two bracelets from gold on my arms,
and I was told in my sleep to blow them away.
So, I blew them and they flew away.
I interpreted that to mean, two liars who would come after me,
One of them is Al-Aswad Al-Ansi(اَسْوَد اَلْعَنْسِيَّ) and the other one is Musaylima(مسيلمه).
Musaylima(مسيلمه) would later write a letter to Rasool Allah ﷺ and this is in the 11th year of Hijrah(هجرة),
he said: And he sent this letter with, two Messengers that came to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ
مِنْ مُسَيْلِمَةَ رَسُولِ اللَّهِ، إلَى مُحَمَّدٍ رَسُولِ اللَّهِ
سَلَامٌ عَلَيْكَ، أَمَّا بَعْدُ، فَإِنِّي قَدْ أُشْرِكْتُ فِي الْأَمْرِ مَعَكَ،
وَإِنَّ لَنَا نِصْفَ الْأَمْرِ ، وَلِقُرَيْشٍ نِصْفَ الْأَمْرِ ، وَلَكِنَّ قُرَيْشًا قَوْمٌ يَعْتَدُونَ
He said: From Musaylim(مسيلمه) The Messenger of Allah, to Muhammad(محمد) the Messenger of Allah
Peace be upon you, I have been involved in the affair with you.
Half of it belongs to us and half of it belongs to Quraish(قريش) but Quraish(قريش) are people who transgress.
So, he's saying that the kingdom needs to be split in half.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wrote back to him.
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَنِ الرَّحِيمِ،
From Muhammad(محمد) the Messenger of Allah to Musaylima(مسيلمه) Al-Kadhhaab(ألكذاب).
السَّلَامُ عَلَى مَنْ اتَّبَعَ الْهُدَى أَمَّا بَعْدُ، فَإِنَّ الْأَرْضَ للَّه يُورَثُهَا مَنْ يُشَاءُ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ، وَالْعَاقِبَةُ لِلْمُتَّقِينَ
Peace be upon those, who follow guidance.
The earth belongs to Allah and He will give it to whomever He wills and the end belongs to the righteous.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ asked them and this is narrated by Abu Dawood Dayalisi(ابوداؤد دعالسي).
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked them;
اَتَشْهَدَانْ اَنِّيْ رَسُوْل الله
Do you testify that I am the messenger of Allah,
they said: We testify that Musaylima(مسيلمه) is the Messenger of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
آمَنْت بِا للهِ وَرَسُلِه
I believe in Allah and His Messengers.
وَلَوْ كُنْتُ قَاتِلًا رَسُوْلاً لَقَتَلْتُكُمَا
And if I was going to kill a Messenger, I would have killed you.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said;
فمَضَتِّ السُّنَّةْ اَنْ الرُسُلْ لَا تَقْتُلْ
Abdullah Ibn Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said: It became Sunnah(سنة) that messengers are not killed,
carriers of letters, the messengers in Islam should not be killed.
Even if they are coming from the enemy, even if they are coming from people of war.
As long as they are a messenger, then they are not to be killed, that is the Sunnah(سنة).
And then there's a delegation that came from Najraan(نجران).
And this is a long story.
You could refer to it in the Tafseer(تفسير) of Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) on the Surah(سورة) of Al-Imran(ألعمران).
Because there was a long dialogue that happened and debate about the difference between Christianity and Islam
and the nature of a Eesa عليه السّلام.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ received the revelation about 80 Ayaat(آيات) from Surah Al-Imran(سورة ألعمران) talking about this,
because the people of Najraan(نجران) were Christian.
Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ) says;
جَاءَ العَاقِبُ وَالسَّيِّدُ ، صَاحِبَا نَجْرَانَ ، إِلَى رَسُولِ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ يُرِيدَانِ أَنْ يُلاَعِنَاهُ
The Aaqib(عاقب) and the Sayed(سيد) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they wanted to do Mula'ana(ملاعنه).
And this is what is referred to also as Mubahala(مباحله)
where Rasool Allah ﷺ would come out and they would come out
and they would ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to send His wrath and punishment on the liars.
And they refused to do so because they said;
If he is truly a Messenger then that will be the end of us and they refuse and they didn't accept that.
Eventually they have to accept the Hukum(حكم) of Rasool Allah ﷺ even though, they didn't become Muslim.
But they would pay Jizyah(جزيه).
So, they said;
إِنَّا نُعْطِيكَ مَا سَأَلْتَنَا ، وَابْعَثْ مَعَنَا رَجُلًا أَمِينًا ، وَلاَ تَبْعَثْ مَعَنَا إِلَّا رَجُلًا أَمِينًا
They said: Sent with us somebody who's trustworthy, and only send the trustworthy man.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَأَبْعَثَنَّ مَعَكُمْ رَجُلًا أَمِينًا حَقَّ أَمِينٍ ،
I will send with you a man who's truly trustworthy.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قُمْ يَا أَبَا عُبَيْدَةَ
Stand up Abu Obaidah(ابو عبيدة).
And this is why Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(عُبَيْدَةَ بْنَ الجَرَّاحِ) is called
أَمِينُ هَذِهِ الأُمَّةِ
The trustworthy man of this Ummah(امة).
And then we have Aamir Bin Tufail(عَامِرِ بْنِ الطُّفَيْلِ) and another man called Rabbad Bin Rabia(أَرْبَدَبن ربيه).
And these are men from Najd(نجد).
And his people told him and he was a head of his people.
يَا أبا عَامِرُ إِنَّ النَّاسَ قَدْ أَسْلَمُوا فَأَسْلِمْ
They told him: Abu Aamir(ابو عامر) people have become Muslim. Why don't you become Muslim?
He said;
وَاللَّهِ لَقَدْ كُنْتُ آلَيْتُ
أَلَّا أَنْتَهِيَ حتَّى تَتْبَعْ اَلْعَرَبْ عَقْبِيْ، فَأَنَا أَتْبَعُ عَقِبَ هَذَا الْفَتَى مِنْ قُرَيْشٍ؟
He said: I have taken a vow that I would not end, meaning my life would not end
until the Arabs Follow me.
And now you want me to follow this young man from Quraish(قريش).
So, you can see the poisoned minds of these men of Jahilliyah(جاهلية).
Where the whole issue of life is seeking power, and greed and authority over others.
So, his whole objective in life is to have the Arabs follow him, walk behind him.
And he doesn't want to become Muslim, because that contradicts with his goal in life.
And people like this do not see the truth and do not follow it.
Because their hearts are too far away from the Fitrah(فطرة).
Their hearts are too attached to false goals of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), which they are chasing like a mirage.
Anyway, they went to Rasool Allah ﷺ, they wanted to strike a deal because they saw that
the Muslims are a force that are to be reckoned with and
if they want to have any authority in the Arabia of the day,
they're going to have to strike a deal with Rasool Allah ﷺ
and they're assuming that Rasool Allah ﷺ is just like them, like their tribal leaders.
So, they want to go and negotiate with him something.
They're not knowing that this is Prophet hood, this is Nabuwwa(نبوة), this is something different.
So, they went to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
فَسَئَلَهْ اَنْ يَجْعَلَ لَهُمْ نِصْفَ الْاَمَرْ
They said: We want you to split the affair between us and you.
فَأَبَى عَلَيْهِمَا رَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused.
فَقَالَ لَه’ عَامِرْ لَعْنَهُ الله أَمَا وَاللَّهِ لَأَمْلَأَنَّهَا عَلَيْكَ خَيْلًا جُرْدًا وَرِجَالً مُرْدًا
In the name of Allah, I'm gonna fill it, meaning Madina, I'm going to fill it, with horses and men.
And he belongs to people, who are numerous, and who are well known as being horsemen
and being good and strong fighters.
So, his threat is not bogus.
I mean, he could truly do that and fill Madina with horses and men
but Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
يَأبى اللهُ عَلَيْكَ ذَالِكْ وَاَبْنَاء الْقَيْلَهْ
Allah would refuse that and the sons of Qayla(قيله),
who are the sons of Qayla(قيله).?
Qayla(قيله) is the mother of the Ansaar(أنْصَار) Al-Aos(الأوس) and Al-Khazraj(الخزرج),
so Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying, Allah refuses that and the sons of Qayla(قيله).
And this shows you the confidence that Rasool Allah ﷺ had in the Ansaar(أنْصَار).
He has tested them and lived with them now, for nine years.
And he has seen their strength and their sacrifice and their willingness to stand with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Now, Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) and Arbad(اربد), they said let's then kill him.
If he refused to negotiate with us, then, let's kill him.
Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) said: I will speak to him and  you come from behind him and strike him with your sword.
So, he would talk to Rasool Allah ﷺ, one narration says,
that the hand of Arbad(اربد) got stuck to the sword, and he couldn't move it,
while the other narration says
that whenever he would try to strike Rasool Allah ﷺ Rasool Ullah would disappear
and he would only see Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) in front of him.
Later on, Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) told him, what's wrong with you?
In the name of Allah, I used to fear no one, as I used to fear you.
And now, I see you as nothing.
Arbad(اربد) told him, what do you want me to do?
Whenever I do tried to strike him, he would disappear.
And you are, the one in front of me.
Did you want me to kill you?
And this is a miracle from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Anyway, they left with empty hands.
And Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) because of that threat, they made to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is the One, Who took care of them.
In the case of Abu Aamir(ابوعامر), on the way he passed by a woman, who belongs to his tribe, and he slept in her house.
By the time he woke up, there was a big swelling in his neck,
some kind of disease afflicted him.
And it is something that kills.
So he didn't want to die in the house of this woman, even though, he was in extreme pain
he went on his horse, and he just kept on wandering until, he died on his horse back.
And that was the end of him.
And with Arbad(اربد), on the way back he was struck by a lightning that killed him, along with his camel.
And they mentioned this as, fulfillment of the Ayah(آية) in Surah Ar-Ra'ad(سورة الرعد),
where Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
هُوَ الَّذِي يُرِيكُمُ الْبَرْقَ خَوْفًا وَطَمَعًا وَيُنْشِئُ السَّحَابَ الثِّقَالَ َ
وَيُسَبِّحُ الرَّعْدُ بِحَمْدِهِ وَالْمَلَائِكَةُ مِنْ خِيفَتِهِ
وَيُرْسِلُ الصَّوَاعِقَ فَيُصِيبُ بِهَا مَنْ يَشَاءُ
وَهُمْ يُجَادِلُونَ فِي اللَّهِ وَهُوَ شَدِيدُ الْمِحَالِ۝
It is He, Who shows you lightning causing fear and aspiration and generates the heavy clouds
and the thunder exalts Allah with praise of Him
and the angels as well, from fear of Him.
And He sends thunderbolts and strikes there with, whom He wills.
While, they dispute about Allah and He is severe in assault.
And that was the end of these two.
Next delegation: They sent one man as a representative of the tribe
and this man, his name is Zumam Bin Thalibah(ضمام بن ثألبه)
there are quite a few narration, some of them in Bukhari(بخاري) and other Books of Hadith(حديث) of the conversation.
There's some difference in wording.
This narration is, the one mentioned by Al-Imam Ahmad(ألإمام أحمد).
It is narrated by Abdullah Ibn Abbas(عبدالله بن عباس).
قَالَ: بَعَثَتْ بَنُو سَعْدِ بْنِ بَكْرٍ ضِمَامَ بْنَ ثَعْلَبَةَ وَافِدًا إِلَى رَسُولِ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ،
Tribe of Bannu Sa'ad Bin Bakr(بنو سعد بن بكر), they sent the Zumam Bin Thalibah(ضمام بن ثألبه) as their representative to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
فَقَدِمَ إِلَيْهِ وَأَنَاخَ بَعِيرَهُ عَلَى بَابِ الْمَسْجِدِ،
ثُمَّ عَلَّقَهُ، ثُمَّ دَخَلَ الْمَسْجِدَ وَرَسُولُ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ جَالِسٌ فِي أَصْحَابِهِ
So, he came, he tied his camel, then he walked into the Masjid(مسجد)
while Rasool Allah ﷺ was sitting with the Sahabah(صحابه).
وَكَانَ ضِمَامٌ رَجُلًا جَلْدًا أَشْعَرَ ذَا غَدِيرَتَيْنِ،
Dhamam(ضمام) was a strong man and he had long hair in two braids.
فَأَقْبَلَ حَتَّى وَقَفَ عَلَى رَسُولِ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ فِي أَصْحَابِهِ،
فَقَالَ: أَيُّكُمُ ابْنُ عَبْدِ الْمُطَّلِبِ؟
So, he said: Who among you is the son of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب)?
And notice here, he didn't say the son of Abdullah(عبدالله), he said the son of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
Because Abdullah(عبدالله) wasn't famous, but Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) was famous all around Arabia.
Remember the important incident of the elephant occurred, when he was the leader of his people.
And he is the one, who went and met with Abrahaa(ابراهة).
So, Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) had a very high status among the Arabs and he was very well known and famous.
So, he said, Where is the son of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
أَنَا
I am the Son of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
قَالَ: مُحَمَّدُ
Are you Muhammad(محمد)? He said: Yes!
فقَالَ:ابْنَ عَبْدِ الْمُطَّلِبِ
You the son of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب), and then he said;
فقَالَ: يَا ابْنَ عَبْدِ الْمُطَّلِبِ إِنِّي سَائِلُكَ وَمُغَلِّظٌ عَلَيْكَ فِي الْمَسْأَلَةِ،
He said, I'm going to ask you, and I'm going to be strict in my questions.
فَلَا تَجِدَنَّ فِي نَفْسِكَ
So, don't be angry.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَا أَجِدُ فِي نَفْسِي،
I'm not going to be angry, ask whatever you want.
فَسَلْ عَمَّا بَدَا لَكَ ". فَقَالَ: أَنْشُدُكَ اللَّهَ إِلَهَكَ، وَإِلَهَ مَنْ كَانَ قَبْلَكَ،
وَإِلَهَ مَنْ هُوَ كَائِنٌ بَعْدَكَ، آللَّهُ بَعَثَكَ إِلَيْنَا رَسُولًا؟
I ask you in the name of Allah, your God, and the God of the ones, before you and the God of the ones, after you!
Did he send you as a Messenger?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اللَّهُمَّ نَعَمْ
Yes! In the name of Allah.
قَالَ: فَأَنْشُدُكَ اللَّهَ إِلَهَكَ، وَإِلَهَ مَنْ كَانَ قَبْلَكَ، وَإِلَهَ مَنْ هُوَ كَائِنٌ بَعْدَكَ،
آللَّهُ أَمَرَكَ أَنَّ تَأْمُرَنَا أَنْ نَعْبُدَهُ وَحْدَهُ، وَلَا نُشْرِكَ بِهِ شَيْئًا
وَأَنْ نَخْلَعَ هَذِهِ الْأَنْدَادَ الَّتِي كَانَ آبَاؤُنَا يَعْبُدُونَ مَعَه’؟
قَالَ: اللَّهُمَّ نَعَمْ
He said: I asked you in the name of Allah, your Lord and the Lord of the ones before you
and the Lord of the ones after you, did Allah ask you to tell us to worship no one but Him,
and to leave these gods that we use to worship?.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes! In the name of Allah.
He said: Then I asked you in the name of Allah, your Lord and the Lord of the ones before you and the Lord of the ones after you,
did Allah order you that we pray these five daily prayers.
He said: In the name of Allah, Yes!
And then he kept on repeating the same thing with all of the five pillars of Islam.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ will give him the same answer and then he said;
قَالَ: فَإِنِّي أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لَا إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ، وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ سَيِّدِنَا مُحَمَّدًا رَسُولُ اللَّهِ،
وَسَأُؤَدِّي هَذِهِ الْفَرَائِضَ، وَأَجْتَنِبُ مَا نَهَيْتَنِي عَنْهُ، ثُمَّ لَا أَزِيدُ وَلَا أَنْقُصُ
He said: I testify that there is no one worthy of worship, but Allah.
And I testify that Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah,
and I am going to fulfill these obligations, and I'm going to leave, what you want me from,
and I'm not gonna add anything or subtract anything.
When he left Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
انْ يَّصْدُقَ ذُو الْعَقِيصَتَيْنِ يَدْخُلُ الْجَنَّةَ
If the man with the two braids is true, truthful, then he will enter into paradise.
And then he went on his camel and left.
He went to his people and as soon as he got there, he said;
Al-Laat(الَّات) and Al-Uzzah(العزة) are evil.
They said: What are you saying, O Dhumam(ضمام)?
You will be afflicted with leprosy, or you would become insane.
He said;
وَيْلَكُمْ، إِنَّهُمَا وَاللَّهِ لَا يَضُرَّانِ
Woe to you, they do not harm and they do not benefit.
Allah has sent the Messenger, and He has revealed to him a book that would save you from what you used to do.
And I testify that there is no God but Allah, and there's no one associated with Him.
And that Muhammad(محمد) is His servant and Messenger and I came to you from him.
And I'm ordering you to do what he ordered me.
And I warned you against the things he warned me from.
By the time that day ended, everyone, men and women in his tribe became Muslim.
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) says;
We never know of a delegation that was more blessed for his people than Zumam Bin Thalibah(ضمام بن ثألبه).
And then we have the story of Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم).
Udae Bin Hatim رضي الله عنه, he heard about the Prophet hood of Muhammadﷺ,
he was a Christian and he didn't like it, he wasn't happy with it.
And he was hearing about the expansion of the Islamic State
and that it was reaching closer and closer to his people, the tribe of Ta'ee(طائ) in North East Arabia.
So, he went to the Roman Empire and he said;
When I reached there, I found it, to be worse than my situation back home.
I mean, he was hating staying back home because of the Muslims coming closer and closer.
But then when he went to the Roman Empire, he found it to be even worse, so he came back.
And it says in a one narration
that he told one of the servants to prepare some very strong camels.
And then he said: Whenever you see the banners of the Muslims approaching, Tell me!
So, his servant did see the banners coming, he told him about it.
So, he took his fast camels and ran away,
so the Muslims came and they took his Aunt and in one narration his sister as Prisoners Of War
and they were brought into Madina.
So, his Aunt total Rasool Allah ﷺ to free her.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ asked her;
Who are you.? So, she told him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told her, you are free.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) told her to ask Rasool Allah ﷺ to provide for you, transportation.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ did so, he was very kind with her.
And she left and she went to Udae(عديئ).
And she told him, what you have done is shameful.
I mean, you ran away and you left your family.
And then she told him, I have come from a man,
who is a Messenger of Allah and he's telling the truth, and she praised Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, he decided to go and visit him because now he was feeling safe about it.
He was feeling that Rasool Allah ﷺ is somebody you could approach and this is a very important thing,
the Mushrikeen(مشركين) of Arabia they would hear false rumors about Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But then when they would hear from people who know him personally
they would see a man, who is merciful and kind and approachable.
And this encouraged many people to come and meet Rasool Allah ﷺ and see him.
But if it was a man, whom they would fear, or they would feel terrorized from
then this would make them very reluctant to go and visit him.
So, Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم), went.
There are different narrations of what happened
One narration says that when he came in, he had the cross hanging on his chest,
you know the customs of the Christians.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
اِتَّخَذُوا أَحْبَارَهُمْ وَرُهْبَانَهُمْ أَرْبَابًا مِنْ دُونِ اللَّهِ
They have taken their priests as Gods besides Allah.
Udae(عديئ) assuming that Rasool Allah ﷺ does not understand about Christianity
and that he's the expert since it's his religion.
So, he said: We do not take them as Gods besides Allah.
Rasool Ullah asked him, didn't they make what was Halal(حلال), Haram(حرام), and what was Halal(حلال) Haram(حرام)?
He said: Yes. He said, then you have worshiped them.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ taught him a meaning of taking them as gods
and that is when you give them the authority to make Halal(حلال), Haram(حرام) and Haram(حرام) Halal(حلال).
Then you have made them as Gods
because this is something that is of the authority of Allah alone.
In another narration Rasool Allah ﷺ told him that,
I understand your religion more than you do.
And he said, so Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم) questioned that, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَلَسْتَ مِنْ رُكُوْسِيَّ
Don't you belong to the sect of Rukusia(روكوسيا)? He said: Yes!
He said and don't you charge your people Al-Murbaa(ألمربآء)
this is what he would take from them, from their spoils.
He said: Yes! He said: That is not allowed in your religion.
And Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم) knew that, that was the case.
He said: As soon as Rasool Allah ﷺ said that I was humbled.
فَتَوَاضَعْتُ لَهَا
In Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ) Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم), he said: We visited Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) in a delegation
فَجَعَل عُمَرُ يَدعُو رَجُلًا رجُلًا ويُسمِّيهم
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) would call them one by one and he would name them
meaning that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) knew them all by name.
فَقلتُ أمَا تَعْرِفُنِي يا أَمِيرَ المؤمنين؟
I asked him, Don't you know me? O Ameer Ul Mo'mineen(امير المؤمنين), because Umar(عمر) did not call him.
He said:
بَلَى أسْلَمْتَ إذْ كَفَرُوا، وأَقْبَلْتَ إذْ أدْبَرُوا، ووَفَيْتَ إذْ غَدَرُوا،
وعَرَفْتَ إذْ أنْكَرُوا. فَقالَ عَدِيٌّ، إذًا لَا أُبَالِي
He said: Yes! I know you. You are the one, who became Muslim when they were disbelievers.
And you are the one, who came, when they left,
and you are the one, who fulfilled when they have betrayed
and you are the one, who knew when they have rejected,
you accepted, when they rejected.
Udae(عديئ) said: Then I do not care, as long as you know that about me then I do not care
meaning he was pleased that the Ameer Ul Momineen(امير المؤمنين) knew about him and recognized him.
By the way, Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم) was the son of the man
who was the most famous Arab in terms of his generosity Hatim Taaee(حاتم طائ), his father.
There are many tales and legends about the generosity of Hatim Taaee(حاتم طائ).
Udae(عديئ) is his son.
In Al-Bukhari(ألبخاريْ) Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم) said;
قَالَ: بَيْنَ أَنَا عِنْدَ النَّبِيِّ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ إِذْ أَتَاهُ رَجُلٌ فَشَكَى إِلَيْهِ الْفَاقَة ثُمَّ وَأَتَاهُ آخر فَشَكَا إِلَيْهِ قَطْعَ الطَّرِيْقْ
Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم), he is a noble man in the society and it comes to Madina
and he sees the situation there.
He was with Rasool Allah ﷺ and a man came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, complaining about poverty
and then another man came and complained about bandits, that are preventing the travelers.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ knowing what Udae(عديئ) is seeing from the situation of Madina.
He told him;
يَا عَدِيَّ هَلْ رَأَيْتَ الْحِيرَةَ
Did you see Al-Heera(الحيره)?
Al-Heera(الحيره) is a city in Iraq.
قُلْتُ: لَمْ أَرَهَا وَقَدْ أُنْبِئْتُ عَنْهَا
I didn't see it, but I have heard about it.
قَالَ: فَإِنْ طَالَتْ بِكَ حَيَاةٌ لَتَرَيَنَّ الظَّعِينَةَ تَرْتَحِلُ مِنَ الْحِيرَةِ حَتَّى تَطُوْفَ بِالْكَعْبَةِ
If you live long enough, you will see a woman traveling from Al-Heera(الحيره),
until she reaches to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) fearing no one but Allah.
قُلْتُ فِيمَا بَيْنِيْ وَبَيْنَ نَفْسِي: فَأَيْنَ دُعَّارُ طَيِّئٍ
I told myself, I was speaking to myself.
Where are the Bandits of Taaee(طيئ).?
الَّذِينَ قَدْ سَعَّرُوا الْبِلَادَ؟
The ones, who have turned the land into fire because
traveling from Heera(حيره) to Makkah you have to pass through the land of Udae(عدئ)
and there were many armed robbers and bandits over there
which makes it impossible for a woman to travel.
And now, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that she would travel fearing no one but Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
وَلَئِنْ طَالَتْ بِكَ حَيَاةٌ لَتُفْتَحَنَّ كُنُوزُ كِسْرَى
قُلْتُ: كِسْرَى بْنُ هُرْمُزَ؟ قَالَ : كِسْرَى بْنُ هُرْمُزَ
And if you live long enough, the treasures of Kisra(كسرى) will become spoils of war for us.
I said: Kisra(كسرى) the son of Hormuz(هرمز) and this is the Persian Emperor
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Kisra(كسرى) the son of Hormuz(هرمز).
وَلَئِنْ طَالَتْ بِكَ حَيَاةٌ لَتَرَيَنَّ الرَّجُلَ يَخْرُجُ بِمِلْءِ كَفِّهِ مِنْ ذَهَبٍ أَوْ فِضَّةٍ
يَطْلُبُ مَنْ يَقْبَلُهُ مِنْهُ فَلَا يَجِدُ أَحَدًا يَقْبَلُهُ مِنْهُ
And if you live long enough, you would find the man coming with a handful of gold or silver
trying to find somebody, who would accept it from him as Sadaqah(صدقه) and he would find no one.
وَلَيَلْقَيَنَّ اللَّهَ أَحَدُكُمْ يَوْمَ يَلْقَاهُ لَيْسَ بَيْنَهُ وَبَيْنَهُ تُرْجُمَانٌ، يُترجِمُ لَه’: فيقولَنَّ لَه’: أَلَمْ أبعَثْ إليك رسولًا فيُبلِّغَكَ؟! فيقول: بلى
To the end of the hadith(حديث)
Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling him about what will happen on the Day of Judgment.
Anyway but Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم) said;
Two of the three things that Rasool Allah ﷺ told me, I have seen with my own eyes
and I'm sure that the third one would happen because it was said by Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
In another narration Rasool Allah ﷺ was telling Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم),
probably the reason, why you don't want to follow me is because you see that we are poor.
Many people go by what they see what is apparent,
and they are affected by the material aspects of things.
They see people wealthy if they see them successful, in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) they're impressed with that.
And this is false and this is wrong.
One should look at the spirit, one should look at the at the essence of the message and not at the material things
because Udae Bin Hatim(عديئ بن حاتم) admitted that this is what was turning him away from Islam.
Because he sees that Muslims are poor people,
they don't have nice houses,
they don't have beautiful roads,
they don't have advanced cities, like we have back home.
And this was turning him away from Islam.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was telling him that
the time will come when we mentioned these things that a woman would travel peacefully
without fearing anybody but Allah,
and that the treasures of Kisra(كسرى) will be spent in the path of Allah.
And then there was a delegation of Al-Ash'areen(ألأشعرين).
Al-Ash'areen(ألأشعرين) are from an area in western Yemen.
In Tahamah(تهامه) in an area called Zabeed(ذبيد)
and they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, in Bukhari(بخاريْ) it says;
عنْ أَبِيْ هُريرَةَ رَضِيَ اللهُ عنه عنَّ النَّبيَّ صلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلم قَالَ:
أَتاكُمْ أهْلُ اليَمَنِ، هُمْ أرَقُّ أفْئِدَةً وأَلْيَنُ قُلُوبًا، الإيمانُ يَمانٍ والحِكْمَةُ يَمانِيَةٌ
When this delegation came to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said according to the narration of Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ).
The people of Yemen have come to you, they are soft hearted.
Eeman(إيمان) is Yemeni! And wisdom is Yemeni!
And this is the praise that Rasool Allah ﷺ has given to the people of Yemen,
that Eeman(إيمان) and Hikmah(حكمة) are Yemeni.
And this was said, when Abu Musa Al-Ashari(ابو موسى الأشعري) and his people came to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then there's a delegation from the Kings of Himyar(حمير) which is also in Yemen.
اَنْ اَنَسْ اِبْنِ مَالِكْ
And this is narrated by Abu Dawood(ابو داؤد),
اَنْ مَالِكْ دِيْعَزَنْ أهدى اِلَى رَسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حُلَّةْ اَخَذَهَا بِثَلَثَةٍ وَثَلَاثِيْنَ بَعيْرَةْ
The Malik Deeazan(مالك ديعزن) has given a gift to Rasool Allah ﷺ
a garment that cost him 33 camels, very expensive
and Rasool Allah ﷺ accepted this gift from him.
And then Jarrir Bin Abdullah Al-Bajali(جرير بن عبد الله البجلي), he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ
according to the narration of Imam Ahmad(امام احمد), Jarrir(جرير) says;
لَمَّا دَنَوْتُ مِنَ المَدِيْنَةِ، أَنَخْتُ رَاحِلَتِي،ثُمَّ حَلَلْتُ عَيْبَتِي، ثُمَّ لَبِسْتُ حُلَّتِي، ثُمَّ دَخَلْتُ المَسْجِدَ، فَإِذَا بِرَسُوْلِ اللهِ صَلَّى اللهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ يَخْطُبُ
Jarrir(جرير), he puts his camel next to the Masjid(مسجد)
and then he entered while Rasool Allah ﷺ was speaking, was giving Khutba(خطبة)
and people were staring at me.
Why are they looking at him?
He assumed that the reason is
because Rasool Allah ﷺ must have said something about him before he came in and that was the case
because he asked someone next to him.
Did Rasool Allah ﷺ mentioned me, he said: Yes!
ذَكَرَكَ آنِفًا بِأَحْسَنِ الذِّكْرِ،
Yes he mentioned you with a very good mentioning
while Rasool Allah ﷺ was speaking in his Khutba(خطبة)
he said, now a man will come in from this door and you would see on his face signs of a King.
He was very handsome, and Rasool Allah ﷺ said: you would see on his face signs of the king.
Jarir(جرير) said;
فَحَمِدْتُ اللهَ عزوجل
I praise the Allahعَزّوجَلّ for that.
And Jarir(جرير) says;
مَا حَجَبَ للنَّبِيْ صلى الله عليه وسلم مُنْذُوْ اَسْلَمْ
Never did Rasool Allah ﷺ refuse meeting me after I became Muslim.
وَلَا رَاَنِيْ  اِلَّا تَبَسَّمَ فِيْ وَجْهِيْ
Whenever he would see me, he would smile in my face.
وَلَقَد شَكَوْتُ اِلَيْهِ اَنِّيْ لَاَثْبُتُ عَلَى الْخَيْلْ
And I told him that I cannot stay firm on horses.
فَضَرَبَ بِيَدِهِ فِي صَدْرِي فَقَالَ: اللَّهُمَّ ثَبِّتْهُ وَاجْعَلْهُ هَادِيًا مَهْدِيًّا
He struck me in my chest and said, O Allah, make him firm
and make him a guided man and guide through him.
Jarir(جرير) said: I never fell off a horse after that.
This is how Rasool Allah ﷺ won the hearts of people
he would smile in their faces.
He would meet them, he was close to his followers.
And then you have another son of Kings of Hazaral Maot(حضزالموت) his name is Wael Bin Hujr(وائل بن هجر).
He came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he met Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه,
and Rasool Ullah hosted him and treated him very well.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ gave him a piece of land.
So, Rasool Ullah wants to show the land the location of the land to him, so he sent Muawiya Ibn Abi Sufiyan(معاويه ابن ابي سفيان) with him.
Muawiya(معاويه) at the time was a young man, unknown,
he was sent with Wael(وائل), to show him the location of the land.
فَأَرْسَلَ مَعِي مُعَاوِيَةَ أَنْ أَعْطِهَا إِيَّاهُ أَوْ قَالَ أَعْلِمْهَا إِيَّاهُ
قَالَ : فَقَالَ لِي مُعَاوِيَةُ : أَرْدِفْنِي خَلْفَكَ ، فَقُلْتُ : لَا تَكُونُ مِنْ أَرْدَافِ الْمُلُوكِ
So, Muawiya(معاويه) is going with Wael(وائل), to guide him to the land
and Wael(وائل) is riding on his camel
and Muawiya(معاويه) is walking and he was walking apparently barefoot or something.
And Muawiya(معاويه) told him, I want to ride with you on your camel,
he said: you're not going to ride with a king and he refused to allow him to ride.
In another narration, it says
that Muawiya(معاويه) told him: I want to ride he said: You are not the king to ride with kings.
And then Muawiya(معاويه) told him the ground is very hot.
So, the Wael(وائل) told him: Use the shade of the camel and walk in it.
So, Muawiya(معاويه) obviously, would not forget how badly he was treated.
And days passed by and Muawiya(معاويه) becomes the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims and who visits him.
Wael Bin Hujr(وائل بن هجر).
So, when Wael came in, Muawiya(معاوية) had him, sit with him, next to him,
on his Sareer(سرير), which is the couch of the king
unlike when he wanted to ride the camel, he was not allowed.
And Muawiya(معاويه) reminded him with what happened that day.
Wael(وائل) would later say;
وَدِدْتُ أَنِّي كُنْتُ حَمَلْتُهُ بَيْنَ يَدَيَّ
I wish that I not only had him ride with me on the camel,
but I wish that I would have him ride in front of me.
And Then there's the delegation of Tamim Ad-Daari(تميم الداري).
And I already talked about this in series on the hereafter
because it's a very long Hadith(حديث) I will not go through it again.
He's the one who reported to Rasool Allah ﷺ the news of meeting Ad-Dajjal(الدجال).
Hadith(حديث) narrated by  Al-Imam Muslim(امام المسلم).
Finally there's the delegation of Al-Asd(الاسد) or a Yemeni tribe that are from the southern part of Arabia.
seven men from Al-Asd(الاسد) came to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ.
By the way, Al-Asd(الاسد) are related to Ansaar(الأنْصَار) because Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) are descendants of Al-Asd(الاسد)
and they came to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ.
فَلَمَّا دَخَلْنَا عَلَيَّه وَكَلَّمْنَاه فَاَعْجَبَهُمْ مَا رَاَى من سَمْكِنَا وَزِيْنَة
Rasool Ullah was impressed by them by their looks, and their characters, and their demeanor.
فَقَالَ: مَا اَنْتُمْ؟
What are you.?
قُلْنَا مُؤْمِنُوْنْ
We said: We are believers
فَتَبَسَّمَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
Rasool Allah smiled and said;
إِنَّ لِكُلِ قَوْلٍ حَقِيقَةً ، فَمَا حَقِيقَةُ قَوْلِكُمْ وَإِيمَانِكُمُ ؟
There's a reality for everything.
So, what is the reality of your statement and your Eeman(إيمان)?
Because they said they're believers.
So, what is the reality of that, what is the manifestation of that?
قُلْنَا : خَمْسَ عَشْرَةَ خَصْلَةً ، خَمْسٌ مِنْهَا أَمَرْتَنَا بِهَا رُسُلُكَ أَنْ نُؤْمِنَ بِهَا
وَ خَمْسٌ أَمَرْتَنَا أَنْ نَعْمَلَ بِهَا ، وَخَمْسٌ تَخَلَّقْنَا بِهَا فِي الجَاهِلِيَّةِ ، فَنَحْنُ عَلَيْهَا الآنَ ، إِلا أَنْ تُكْرَهَ مِنْهَا شَيْئاً
15 characteristics five of them were commanded by your Messengers to us,
five of them you have commanded us to do
and five of them were traditions from the time of Jahilliyah(جاهليه),
except if you want us to change them.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: What are the five which my messengers order you.?
قُلْنَا : " أَمَرْتَنَا أَنْ نُؤْمِنْ بِاللهِ ، وَمَلاَئِكَتِهِ ، وَكُتُبِهِ ، وَرُسِلِهِ ، وَالبَعْثِ بَعْدَ المَوْتِ " ،
We are ordered to believe in Allah, His angels, His books,
His Messengers and Resurrection after death.
قَالَ : " وَمَا الخَمْسُ الَّتِي أَمَرْتُكُم أَنْ تَعْمَلُوا بِهَا ؟ "
What are the five commands that I gave you,
قُلْنَا : " أَمَرْتَنَا أَنْ نَقُوْلَ : " لاَ إِلَهَ إِلاَّ اللهَ ، وَنُقِيْمَ الصَّلاَةَ ، وَنُؤْتِيَ الزَّكَاةَ ، وَنَصُوْمَ رَمَضَانَ ، ونَحُجَّ البَيْتَ الحَرَامِ مَنِ اسْتَطَاعَ إِلَيْهِ سَبِيْلاً "
You order us to say La illaha illallah(لا اله الا الله), and to establish Salah(صلاة)
and to pays Zakah(زكوة) and to fast Ramadan(رمضان) and to make Hajj(حَجْ) for the one, who's capable.
" وَمَا الخَمْسُ الَّتِي تَخَلَّقْتُم بِهَا فِي الجَاهِلِيَّةِ ؟ " ،
And what are the five, which you have made as your character, in the time of Jahilliyah(جاهلية).
قَالُوْا :  الشُّكْرُ عِنْدَ الرَّخَاءِ ،
وَ الصَّبْرُ عِنْدَ البَلاَءِ ،
وَالرِّضَى بِمُرِّ القَضَاءِ ،
وَالصِّدْقُ فِي موَاطنِ اللِّقَاءِ ،
وَتَرْكُ الشَّمَاتَةِ بِالأَعْدَاءِ
Again the five,
اَلشُّكْرُ عِنْدَ الرَّخَاءِ
Being grateful in times of ease.
وَ الصَّبْرُ عِنْدَ البَلاَءِ
And being patient in times of difficulty.
وَالرِّضَى بِمُرِّ القَضَاءِ ،
And to accept destiny.
وَالصِّدْقُ فِي موَاطنِ اللِّقَاءِ ،
And being truthful when the enemies meet.
وَتَرْكُ الشَّمَاتَةِ بِالأَعْدَاءِ
And avoiding malicious joy out of our enemies.
Meaning they do not go to extremes, in making fun of their enemies,
they are decent even with the enemy.
فَقَالَ رَسُولُ الله صَلَّى الله عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ : " حُكَمَاءُ عُلَمَاءُ كَادُوا مِنْ فِقههم أَنْ يَكُوْنُوا أَنْبِيَاءَ "
You are wise and knowledgeable
and you have almost because of your knowledge you have almost become Prophets.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was very impressed by their wisdom.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
وَأَنَا أَزِيْدُكُم خَمْساً ، فَيتِمُّ لَكُم عِشْرُوْنَ خَصْلَةً
And I will give you five more, so you will have 20 characteristics.
إِنْ كُنْتُمْ كَمَا تَقُوْلُوْنَ ،
If what you're saying is true, if you are like, what you say.
فَلا تَجَمَّعُوا مَا لا تَأْكُلُوْنَ
Do not collect what you will not eat.
وَلا تَبْنُوا مَا لا تَسْكُنُونَ ،
And do not build, what you will not live in,
وَلا تُنَافَسُوا فِي شَيْءٍ أَنْتُم عَنْهُ غَداً تَزُولُونَ
And do not compete in something that you will leave tomorrow,
وَاتَّقُوا اللهَ الذي إِلَيْهِ تُرْجِعُوْنَ وَعَلَيْهِ تُعْرَضُون
And fear Allah, Whom you will return to and Whom you will be presented to.
وَ ارْغَبُوا فِيمَا عليه تَقْدمُونَ ، وَفِيهِ تَخْلُدُونَ
And strive for, what you are facing ahead of you,
and where you will be living forever, meaning, the afterlife.
فَانْصَرَفَ القَوْمُ مِنْ عِنْدِ رَسُوْلِ اللهِ صَلَّى اللهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ ، وَحَفِظُوا وَصِيَّتَهُ ، عَمِلُوا بِهَا
And they left and they followed the advice of Rasool Allah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
We have only covered some of the delegations that came to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, you can see that it was a busy year, where people are coming and accepting Islam
from the four corners of the Arabian Peninsula.
And this is towards the end of the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He is now witnessing the fruit of his Daw'ah(دعوة).
He is now harvesting the fruit of the seed which he planted in Makkah
in the early days when it was very difficult.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ is seeing the manifestation of his efforts due to the blessing of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and the Barakah(بركة) that Allahعَزّوجَلّ has put in his Daw'ah(دعوة).
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته